<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>
<properties>
  <title>BreakTest Features And Differences</title>
</properties>
<body>

<section name="BreakTest Features And Differences">
<p>
This is the BreakTest manual. It documents the features and behavioral changes
that are specific to BreakTest 2026.07.11. For the inherited JMeter-compatible
test-plan model, use the official Apache JMeter documentation.
</p>

<h2>Runtime Baseline</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Java 21 or later is required.</li>
  <li>Virtual threads are used where they reduce thread overhead.</li>
  <li>Legacy BeanShell, BSF/JEXL2, Rhino JavaScript, and LogKit paths were removed from the modern scripting/runtime surface.</li>
  <li>JMeter-compatible names are retained where they are part of file formats, APIs, plugins, scripts, or automation.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Modern HTTP And HTTP/2</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The built-in HTTP sampler path uses Apache HttpClient 5.</li>
  <li>HTTP/2 and HTTP/2-preferred protocol selection are available through the async HttpClient 5 path.</li>
  <li>BreakTest handles negotiated fallback, HTTP/2 upload content length, connect-time reporting, and safer replay behavior.</li>
  <li>HTTP/2 resource usage was reduced by limiting reactor threads and avoiding unnecessary client/reactor rebuilds between same-user iterations.</li>
  <li>NTLM authentication was fixed on the HttpClient 5 path, including variable resolution before async authentication callbacks.</li>
  <li>Brotli and Zstandard response decoding were added alongside gzip and deflate.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Lower Runtime Resource Usage</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Lazy response decompression stores compressed bytes and decompresses only when response data is accessed.</li>
  <li>Response retention modes can keep compressed data, discard successful bodies, keep only failing bodies, or retain MD5 checksums.</li>
  <li>Lightweight test-plan cloning reduces per-thread object churn.</li>
  <li>Header merging, temporary property handling, response read buffers, and diagnostic metadata paths were optimized.</li>
  <li>Rich sample diagnostics are lazy and listener-driven, so normal load runs avoid unnecessary per-sample storage.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Unified Scheduling</h2>
<p>
BreakTest moves load modeling into a unified Thread Group rather than splitting
common scenarios across several specialized thread groups.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Closed-model schedules can combine different ramp-up speeds, hold periods, and target thread counts.</li>
  <li>Open-model schedules can model arrivals, use even-arrival helpers, and cap active threads.</li>
  <li>Thread Group pacing controls are available for transaction pacing.</li>
  <li>Schedule parsing is safer and includes graph preview support.</li>
  <li>Runtime user variables are cleared on new iterations when same-user mode is disabled, while initial variables are preserved.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Pause, Resume, And Faster Shutdown</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Pause and Resume are available in the GUI and through <code>bin/pause.*</code> and <code>bin/resume.*</code>.</li>
  <li>In closed model, pause holds active threads and stops further ramp-up.</li>
  <li>In open model, pause stops new arrivals and lets active threads finish naturally, so load drops while paused.</li>
  <li>Shutdown no longer waits for timers to complete; it waits for in-flight server responses to finish cleanly.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Parallel And Fork Controllers</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Parallel Controller runs child samplers concurrently with bounded scheduling.</li>
  <li>Fork Controller starts asynchronous child branches that share virtual-user context and complete before thread teardown.</li>
  <li>HTTP state handling was tightened to reduce unsafe sharing in concurrent paths.</li>
</ul>

<h2>AI-Assisted Scripting</h2>
<p>
BreakTest includes local agent and MCP support for AI-assisted script repair.
Tools such as Codex, Claude Code, and opencode can inspect a JMX script,
validate it, repair it, and show changes in the GUI.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Create or repair extractors and correlations.</li>
  <li>Parameterize dynamic values.</li>
  <li>Add assertions.</li>
  <li>Fix selectors and unstable recorded data.</li>
  <li>Review generated changes from the GUI before continuing.</li>
</ul>

<h2>GUI And Large JMX Improvements</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Cleaner light/dark GUI styling.</li>
  <li>Undo and redo for semantic tree edits including add, delete, update, move, and search/replace operations.</li>
  <li>Background JMX loading with a loading overlay.</li>
  <li>Optional fast GUI loading through <code>breaktest.gui.load.fast=true</code>.</li>
  <li>Missing plugin elements load as disabled placeholders instead of failing the whole file.</li>
  <li>Search Tree can flag pre-processors, post-processors, assertions, timers, and config elements.</li>
  <li>Search results can be removed selectively with confirmation.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Visual Debugging And HAR Migration</h2>
<ul>
  <li>View Results Tree shows richer request, response, endpoint, HTTP/TLS, cookie, variable, and binary/text diagnostics.</li>
  <li>Jump-to-source support connects samples back to test elements.</li>
  <li>BreakTest JMX metadata preserves origin and source-path details.</li>
  <li>When BreakTest HAR metadata is present, recorded request/response tabs are shown in View Results Tree and HTTP sampler editors.</li>
  <li>Recorded-vs-replayed diffs help debug HAR migration and HTTP/2 replay.</li>
  <li>Transaction child samples preserve source paths so folded transaction results can still navigate to the correct source element.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Scripting, Data, And Assertions</h2>
<ul>
  <li>If and While Controllers support structured condition rows with all/any matching while preserving legacy expressions.</li>
  <li>Loop and while index behavior options are visible and configurable.</li>
  <li>Transaction Controller includes measurement modes plus delay and pacing controls.</li>
  <li>Boundary, CSS/HTML, Regex, XPath, XPath2, JSONPath, and JMESPath extractors support fail-on-no-match behavior.</li>
  <li>CSV Data Set can read records in random order.</li>
  <li>CSV preview shows first sample variable assignments.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Native UDP</h2>
<ul>
  <li>UDP Request sends datagrams with optional response waiting, response timeout, local address and port binding, and socket reuse.</li>
  <li>UDP Receiver can read a later datagram from a named socket created by UDP Request.</li>
  <li>A friendly payload-format selector provides UTF-8 text, hexadecimal, and single-byte text; advanced custom codecs can implement the native <code>UDPTrafficCodec</code> interface.</li>
  <li>The implementation uses the Java networking API directly and does not require the JMeter Plugins common I/O or common JMeter libraries.</li>
</ul>
<p>See <a href="udp-request.html">Native UDP Request And Receiver</a> for configuration details.</p>

<h2>Removed Or Changed Compatibility Areas</h2>
<ul>
  <li>RMI Remote Server style distributed execution is removed. Use BreakTest Enterprise or another controlled orchestration layer for distributed runs.</li>
  <li>BreakTest-specific JMX metadata may not round-trip into older Apache JMeter versions.</li>
  <li>Plugins that depend on removed internals may require migration.</li>
  <li>HttpClient 4 runtime jars remain available for legacy plugin compatibility, but the built-in HTTP Request sampler uses HttpClient 5.</li>
</ul>

</section>
</body>
</document>
