<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE document[
<!ENTITY sect-num '2'>
]>

<document prev="get-started.html" next="build-test-plan.html" id="$Id$">
<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: BreakTest Features</title>
</properties>
<body>

<section name="&sect-num;. BreakTest Features" anchor="breaktest_features">
<p>
BreakTest keeps the JMX test-plan model and many JMeter-compatible names for
compatibility, but it is not a frozen copy of Apache JMeter. This page
summarizes the main BreakTest-specific capabilities and where they affect test
design.
</p>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.1 Java 21+ runtime" anchor="java21">
<p>
BreakTest requires Java 21 or later. The newer baseline allows the runtime to
use modern JVM behavior, including virtual-thread support where it helps
concurrency and resource usage.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.2 Modern HTTP and HTTP/2" anchor="http2">
<p>
The built-in HTTP sampler path uses Apache HttpClient 5 and includes HTTP/2
support. Legacy HttpClient 4 jars remain bundled for plugin compatibility, but
new built-in HTTP behavior should be tested against the HttpClient 5 path.
</p>
<p>
BreakTest also improves response handling with Brotli and Zstandard decoding,
lazy decompression, and response retention modes that can reduce memory
pressure during larger runs.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.3 Scheduling, pause/resume, and load models" anchor="scheduling">
<p>
The unified Thread Group supports closed and open workload models. Closed-model
phases can combine different ramp-up speeds, hold periods, and target thread
counts. Open-model helpers can model arrivals and cap active threads.
</p>
<p>
Pause and Resume are available from the GUI and command wrappers. In a closed
model, pausing holds active threads instead of continuing the ramp. In an open
model, new arrivals are paused and active threads finish naturally, so load
drops while paused.
</p>
<p>
Shutdown is quicker than historical JMeter behavior: shutdown no longer waits
for timers to complete and only waits for in-flight server responses to finish
cleanly.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.4 Parallel and forked work" anchor="parallel">
<p>
The Parallel Controller can run child samplers concurrently with bounded
parallelism. The Fork Controller can start asynchronous child branches that
share virtual-user context and complete before thread teardown.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.5 AI-assisted scripting" anchor="ai_scripting">
<p>
BreakTest includes local-agent support for AI-assisted scripting. Tools such as
Codex, Claude Code, and opencode can use the BreakTest MCP server and local
agent tooling to inspect a JMX file, validate it, repair selectors and
correlation, parameterize dynamic values, add assertions, and rerun checks.
</p>
<p>
When used from the GUI, BreakTest can highlight changes made by the repair
workflow so you can review the generated edits before continuing.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.6 GUI editing and large JMX files" anchor="gui">
<p>
BreakTest adds undo/redo for common semantic tree edits, background JMX loading,
safe missing-plugin placeholders, and lighter loading paths for large plans.
Search Tree can flag elements with pre-processors, post-processors, assertions,
timers, and config elements, and can remove matching elements with confirmation.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.7 Visual debugging and HAR migration" anchor="visual_debugging">
<p>
View Results Tree includes richer HTTP/TLS/cookie/request/response diagnostics
and source navigation. When BreakTest HAR metadata is present, recorded
request/response tabs and recorded-vs-replayed diffs help debug migration and
HTTP/2 replay behavior.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.8 Scripting, data, and assertions" anchor="scripting_data">
<p>
BreakTest improves If and While Controller conditions with structured rows,
adds transaction delay and pacing controls, supports random CSV ordering and CSV
preview, and adds fail-on-no-match options across common extractors.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.9 Compatibility notes" anchor="compatibility">
<p>
Existing JMeter JMX files remain supported where practical. Many package names,
properties, log file names, and internal identifiers intentionally still contain
<code>jmeter</code> or <code>org.apache.jmeter</code> because changing them would
break existing test plans and plugins.
</p>
<p>
BreakTest-specific JMX metadata and features may not round-trip into older
Apache JMeter versions. RMI Remote Server style distributed execution has been
removed; use BreakTest Enterprise or another controlled orchestration layer for
distributed runs.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>
</body>
</document>
