<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE document
[
<!ENTITY sect-num '25'>
]>
<document id="$Id$" prev="curl.html" >

<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: History and Future</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="&sect-num;. History and Future" anchor="history_future">
<subsection name="&sect-num;.1 History" anchor="history">
<p>
BreakTest started as an independent fork of Apache JMeter 5.6.3. The goal was
to keep the familiar JMX test-plan model while modernizing the runtime, user
interface, HTTP stack, scheduling model, diagnostics, and script-repair workflow
for current performance-testing teams.
</p>
<p>
BreakTest is a derivative work of Apache JMeter and retains the required
copyright, license, notice, package, and compatibility references. BreakTest is
independent from The Apache Software Foundation and is not affiliated with,
endorsed by, or sponsored by The Apache Software Foundation.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.2 The Future" anchor="future">
<p>
BreakTest development is focused on making local script creation, debugging,
and validation faster while keeping a clear path to scaled execution and deeper
analysis through BreakTest Enterprise.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Continue improving HTTP/2 and modern HTTP behavior.</li>
<li>Reduce memory and CPU overhead in large tests and large JMX files.</li>
<li>Improve open and closed workload modeling, pacing, pause/resume, and schedule visualization.</li>
<li>Expand visual diagnostics for recorded-vs-replayed traffic, correlation, assertions, and source navigation.</li>
<li>Make AI-assisted script repair more reliable and easier to review from the GUI.</li>
<li>Keep compatibility with existing JMeter JMX files where practical, while documenting intentional differences clearly.</li>
</ul>
<note>You can help by opening issues and pull requests in the BreakTest GitHub repository. See <a href="../building.html">Building and Contributing to BreakTest</a>.</note>
</subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>
