<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>
<properties>
  <title>Native UDP Request And Receiver</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Native UDP Request And Receiver">
<p>
BreakTest includes UDP support in its standard distribution. No JMeter Plugins
common I/O or common JMeter library is required. Add <b>UDP Request</b> or
<b>UDP Receiver</b> from a test-plan node's <b>Sampler</b> menu.
</p>

<h2>UDP Request</h2>
<ul>
  <li><b>Hostname or IP address</b> and <b>Destination port</b> select the remote endpoint.</li>
  <li><b>Response timeout</b> is the maximum receive wait in milliseconds. Zero waits indefinitely.</li>
  <li><b>Wait for response</b> receives one datagram after sending. The operating system reassembles IP fragments before BreakTest receives it, but separate UDP datagrams are not combined. Clear the option for fire-and-forget traffic.</li>
  <li><b>Local bind address</b> and <b>Local bind port</b> control the source interface and port. A blank port uses an ephemeral port.</li>
  <li><b>Close socket after request</b> closes an unnamed socket after each sample. Named sockets stay open for reuse.</li>
  <li><b>Allow unexpected disconnect</b> treats an ICMP port-unreachable result as a successful sample.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Payload Codecs</h2>
<p>
Choose a friendly <b>Payload format</b> from the sampler. The default
<b>Text (UTF-8)</b> option accepts normal text. <b>Hexadecimal bytes</b> accepts
pairs of hexadecimal digits and exposes responses as lowercase hexadecimal.
<b>Single-byte text (ISO-8859-1)</b> maps each request character directly to
one byte for legacy protocols. The <b>Custom codec class</b> option accepts a
public no-argument class that implements
<code>org.apache.jmeter.protocol.udp.sampler.UDPTrafficCodec</code>.
</p>

<h2>Named Sockets And UDP Receiver</h2>
<p>
A non-empty <b>Socket ID</b> shares one connected socket within the current
virtual user. Different virtual users always get separate sockets, even when
they use the same Socket ID. This prevents responses from being consumed by
the wrong user.
The first UDP Request for an ID must provide the remote endpoint and optional
local bind settings. Later UDP Requests can provide only the same Socket ID;
they use the endpoint and binding of the already-open socket. Repeating the
endpoint fields remains useful when a sampler should also be able to create
the socket, and BreakTest verifies that repeated settings match.
Use the same ID in UDP Receiver to collect a later or unsolicited datagram.
Operations on a named socket are serialized. Reusing an ID with different
remote or local bind settings fails explicitly, and named sockets close when
the virtual user finishes.
</p>
<p>
UDP Receiver can treat a timeout as either a successful no-content sample or a
failed request. The receive buffer is reused between samples and defaults to
the maximum UDP payload size. It can be reduced with the
<code>udp.receive_buffer_size</code> property. A response exceeding a reduced
limit fails with response code <code>413</code> instead of being silently
truncated.
</p>

<h2>Payload Size And Fragmentation</h2>
<p>
BreakTest rejects payloads larger than the protocol maximum before sending
them: 65,507 bytes over IPv4 or 65,527 bytes over IPv6. Requests larger than a
typical Ethernet UDP payload produce a one-time log warning because IP
fragmentation makes loss more likely. Change the warning threshold with
<code>udp.fragmentation_warning_size</code>, or set it to zero to disable the
warning.
</p>
<p>
IP fragmentation is transparent to the sampler: the operating system either
delivers one fully reassembled UDP datagram or discards it when reassembly
fails, in which case the sampler times out. Multiple application-level UDP
datagrams are independent messages and require protocol-specific sequence or
length fields; BreakTest does not concatenate them automatically.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
