<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>
<properties>
    <author email="info@breaking-it.nl">BreakTest developers</author>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Release Notes">
<note>
BreakTest requires Java 21 or later. BreakTest 2026.07.10 is licensed under
the Apache License, Version 2.0.
</note>

<h1>Version 2026.07.10</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.10 is a workflow, visualization, and scalability release
built from the changes since BreakTest 2026.07.08. It adds direct HAR import,
parallel ForEach execution, a richer View Results listener, and targeted
runtime and desktop performance improvements.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added a guided HAR import wizard for <code>.har</code> and <code>.har.gz</code> recordings, with hostname filtering, request grouping, delay options, and automatic test-plan generation.</li>
  <li>Added optional parallel execution to the ForEach Controller, with configurable maximum concurrency and lazy branch creation for very large collections.</li>
  <li>Expanded View Results with a table layout, selectable columns, response-time data, request and response sizes, URLs, filtering, and improved status icons.</li>
  <li>Reduced repeated test-tree traversal by caching parent-controller paths used by loop control actions.</li>
  <li>Added the HTTP request URL to the Sampler Result text view and made the initial test-plan pane width configurable.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>HAR Import</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added <b>File &gt; Import HAR...</b> and a matching HAR toolbar action.</li>
  <li>Added guided steps for selecting a HAR file, choosing hostnames, and configuring import behavior.</li>
  <li>Added support for ignoring recorded error responses, continuing on error, adding request indexes, detecting dynamic URLs, and splitting transactions using recorded idle gaps.</li>
  <li>Added recorded, fixed, random, Gaussian, and disabled transaction-delay modes.</li>
  <li>Generated plans can include Transaction Controllers, Parallel Controllers for concurrent requests, HTTP Request Defaults, Cookie Managers, assertions, shared headers, and request-local headers.</li>
  <li>Preserved BreakTest HAR metadata so imported requests remain compatible with recorded-HAR inspection and repair workflows.</li>
  <li>Fixed reference and variable handling in imported requests.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Parallel ForEach and Runtime Performance</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added <b>Parallel execution</b> and <b>Maximum parallel executions</b> options to the ForEach Controller.</li>
  <li>Branches are created only when a concurrency slot becomes available, so very large collections do not prebuild every controller branch.</li>
  <li>Transaction-controller source mappings are scoped to each active branch and released with that branch, keeping retained execution state proportional to configured parallelism rather than total item count.</li>
  <li>Preserved branch-local ForEach output values while sharing the surrounding virtual-user context and honoring existing same-user iteration behavior.</li>
  <li>Added parent-path caching for loop actions that previously traversed the test tree repeatedly after errors or logical loop transitions.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Results and Desktop Experience</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added Tree and Table modes to View Results, with table results above the detail pane and the existing tree and detail split retained in Tree mode.</li>
  <li>Added timestamp, time, latency, connect time, request size, response size, thread group, thread name, label, and URL columns with configurable visibility.</li>
  <li>Added filtering by thread group, thread name, and sampler label, including a table context-menu action for filtering to a selected thread.</li>
  <li>Fixed automatic scrolling and filter controls during live table refreshes.</li>
  <li>Added full-value tooltips for truncated table cells and numeric sorting for timing and size columns.</li>
  <li>Modernized success and failure icons and added HTTP URLs to the Sampler Result text tab.</li>
  <li>Set a stable startup width for the test-plan pane, configurable through <code>jmeter.gui.testplan.width</code>.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Benchmarks and Tests</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added high-capacity ForEach benchmarks covering active-window memory, representative sample payloads, and parent-mode Transaction Controllers.</li>
  <li>Added regression tests for lazy branch creation, bounded transaction mapping, branch-local variables, parent transactions, table sorting, filtering, automatic scrolling, URL display, and visualizer layout behavior.</li>
  <li>Expanded HAR conversion tests across grouping, headers, request bodies, delay modes, hostname filtering, and generated configuration elements.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility Notes</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Java 21 or later is still required.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li>Parallel ForEach execution is opt-in; existing ForEach Controllers remain sequential unless explicitly enabled.</li>
  <li>This release uses the direct Git tag <code>2026.07.10</code> rather than a <code>rel/...</code> prefix.</li>
</ul>

<h1>Version 2026.07.08</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.08 is a focused stability and GUI-assistance release built
from the changes since BreakTest 2026.07.07. It keeps the same Java 21+
baseline while improving fork and parallel execution, AI-assisted GUI repair
actions, and day-to-day desktop ergonomics.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Fixed Fork Controller lifecycle cleanup so completed forks are removed while the parent virtual user keeps running.</li>
  <li>Added <code>ctx.getThread().stopForks()</code> and <code>ctx.getThread().stopForksNow()</code> for Groovy/JSR223 scripts that need to end active fork branches from the main thread.</li>
  <li>Improved fork shutdown so timers, pacing waits, active fork samplers, and virtual-thread fork workers are woken promptly.</li>
  <li>Fixed fork branch behavior for "Start Next Thread Loop on error" so failed fork samples stop the fork branch locally instead of continuing to later requests.</li>
  <li>Hardened Parallel Controller execution so nested loop branches keep their own loop indexes and sampler package configuration is synchronized safely across concurrent branches.</li>
  <li>Added a GUI-backed <code>clone_node_open_plan</code> MCP tool so AI-assisted repair can copy full controller/sampler subtrees, including Transaction Controller pacing settings, without falling back to raw JMX reconstruction.</li>
  <li>Improved AI Helper and log-panel usability with Shift+Enter newlines in the JSR223 AI Helper prompt and a visible bottom-log resize boundary.</li>
  <li>Reduced noisy delay-interruption warnings during intentional fork and test stops.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Fork and Parallel Controller Stability</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Completed fork tasks, executors, and active-controller mappings are now cleaned up promptly instead of waiting for thread teardown.</li>
  <li>Fork workers now track current timers, samplers, and worker threads so graceful and forced fork stops can wake the correct in-flight operation.</li>
  <li><code>stopForks()</code> requests graceful fork completion and wakes fork timers without stopping the main virtual user.</li>
  <li><code>stopForksNow()</code> cancels active fork tasks, shuts down fork executors, and stops fork samplers that implement <code>StoppableSampler</code>.</li>
  <li>Intentional fork-stop interruptions no longer emit WARN-level "Loss of delay" timer messages.</li>
  <li>Fork timer/sampler bookkeeping now removes active entries by identity so equally configured sibling branches cannot remove the wrong entry.</li>
  <li>Fork branches now consume local logical error actions and reset <code>LAST_SAMPLE_OK</code> so fork control-flow decisions do not leak into the main virtual-user path.</li>
  <li>Parallel branch sampler configuration is protected from concurrent compiler state corruption.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>AI-Assisted GUI Repair</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added <code>clone_node_open_plan</code> to the BreakTest MCP bridge for cloning a node and its complete child subtree in the live GUI plan.</li>
  <li>The clone tool supports stable <code>nodeId</code> selectors from <code>find_open_plan_nodes</code> and path/index fallbacks, matching the existing move/delete structural tools.</li>
  <li>The clone operation uses the same full subtree copy path as the GUI Duplicate action, preserving element properties and children rather than rebuilding controllers from partial fields.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Desktop Polish</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>The docked Logs / AI Auto Scripting panel now has a visible top divider and a wider split-pane drag target, making the resize area discoverable without hovering.</li>
  <li>The JSR223 AI Helper request text area now treats Shift+Enter as an explicit newline.</li>
  <li>Extractor and post-processor icons in the test-plan tree were aligned more closely with the Add menu iconography.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Benchmarks and Tests</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added a JMH benchmark for Fork Controller capacity, including lightweight and more representative fork branch scenarios.</li>
  <li>Added regression tests for fork cleanup, fork stopping, fork error handling, nested parallel loop indexes, and tree icon rendering.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility Notes</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Java 21 or later is still required.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li><code>stopForks()</code> and <code>stopForksNow()</code> are BreakTest extensions intended for scripts that explicitly need to manage asynchronous fork branches.</li>
</ul>

<h1>Version 2026.07.07</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.07 is a focused desktop and reporting update built from the
changes since BreakTest 2026.07.03. It keeps the same Java 21+ baseline and
JMeter-compatible test-plan model while improving the GUI workflow, settings
management, validation, and live performance reporting.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added a configurable Performance Report listener with percentile, throughput, bandwidth, error, and connect-time columns.</li>
  <li>Added a Settings dialog backed by the full JMeter properties catalog, with search, default/modified indicators, reset controls, and safe persistence to local override property files.</li>
  <li>Modernized the BreakTest desktop UI with a refreshed application icon, modern toolbar icons, cleaner tree rendering, improved menu organization, and better light/dark FlatLaf styling.</li>
  <li>Improved View Results Tree and validation ergonomics with detach/dock support, validation targeting, auto-detach controls, collapsible search/file panels, and comment visibility controls.</li>
  <li>Moved sampler-scoped HTTP headers into the HTTP Request sampler with automatic migration from child HTTP Header Manager elements.</li>
  <li>Fixed saved test plans with the new Performance Report listener so they reload correctly.</li>
  <li>Added child-count badges in the test-plan tree and compact Transaction Controller delay summaries beside transaction names.</li>
  <li>Added counts to HTTP Request Params, Headers, Body, and Files tabs so hidden request data is visible at a glance.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Performance Reporting</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added a dedicated Performance Report visualizer for configurable live aggregate metrics.</li>
  <li>Added optional percentile columns including median, P75, P90, P95, and P99.</li>
  <li>Added controls to ignore error response times in response-time metrics.</li>
  <li>Added resource-use guidance for percentile columns, since they retain richer response-time distribution data while enabled.</li>
  <li>Added tests for column configuration, percentile tracking, error handling, and report reset behavior.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Settings Management</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added a Settings page available from the GUI menu and toolbar.</li>
  <li>Added typed setting definitions, editors, grouping, search, default-value display, modified badges, and reset/save actions.</li>
  <li>Added a full settings catalog resource for JMeter and BreakTest properties.</li>
  <li>Persisted changes to local user/system override properties rather than modifying the bundled <code>jmeter.properties</code> file.</li>
  <li>Added tests for catalog loading, property storage, and model behavior.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Desktop UI and Validation</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Refreshed the main frame, toolbar, menu factory, tree renderer, logger panel, target-rate chart, and scripting log presentation.</li>
  <li>Added modern SVG toolbar assets and updated icon mappings for common actions.</li>
  <li>Improved validation controls so selected thread groups can be targeted more directly.</li>
  <li>Added View Results Tree detach/dock workflows and clearer validation result viewing.</li>
  <li>Added native HTTP Request headers so sampler-specific headers live on the request itself, while higher-level Header Managers still apply by scope.</li>
  <li>Updated the Transaction Controller icon so it reads as a transaction span rather than a small generic controller/action glyph.</li>
  <li>Added direct-child count badges to tree nodes and compact delay summaries for Transaction Controllers with built-in delay.</li>
  <li>Added value counts to HTTP Request data tabs for Params, Headers, Body, and Files.</li>
  <li>Added tests around tree-listener behavior.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility Notes</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Java 21 or later is still required.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li>Percentile columns in the Performance Report intentionally keep additional response-time history only while those columns are selected.</li>
  <li>Most Settings changes are written as local overrides and take effect after restarting BreakTest.</li>
</ul>

<h1>Version 2026.07.03</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.03 is an independent, JMeter-compatible continuation focused
on a leaner runtime, modern HTTP support, better debugging, AI-assisted script
repair workflows, and a smoother path from local scripts to scaled execution.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Modern HTTP runtime based on Apache HttpClient 5, including first-class HTTP/2 support.</li>
  <li>Java 21+ baseline with virtual-thread support.</li>
  <li>Lower memory and CPU pressure through lazy decompression, response retention modes, lightweight cloning, lazy diagnostics, and allocation reductions.</li>
  <li>Unified Thread Group scheduling with closed/open workload models, phases, open-model helpers, pacing, and pause/resume support.</li>
  <li>Parallel Controller and Fork Controller for realistic concurrency and independent branches of work.</li>
  <li>Undo/redo support for common GUI test-plan edits.</li>
  <li>Background JMX loading, fast GUI loading options, and safer placeholders for missing plugin elements.</li>
  <li>Richer View Results Tree diagnostics, source navigation, and HAR-backed recorded-vs-replayed request/response diff views.</li>
  <li>Easier If/While controller conditions, transaction timing controls, random CSV ordering, CSV preview, and extractor fail-on-no-match options.</li>
  <li>AI-assisted scripting support through the BreakTest MCP workflow, including visible GUI change highlighting when scripts are repaired automatically.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Modern HTTP Runtime</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added Apache HttpClient 5 sampler support for HTTP/1.1.</li>
  <li>Added an async HttpClient 5 HTTP/2 sampler path with HTTP/2 and HTTP/2-preferred protocol selection.</li>
  <li>Added negotiated fallback, connect-time reporting, HTTP/2 upload content length handling, and safer HTTP/2 replay behavior.</li>
  <li>Reduced HTTP/2 resource usage by limiting reactor threads by default and avoiding unnecessary async client/reactor rebuilds between same-user iterations.</li>
  <li>Added conservative HTTP/2 closed-session retry handling for common connection-closure failures.</li>
  <li>Fixed NTLM authentication on the HttpClient 5 path, including variable resolution before async authentication callbacks.</li>
  <li>Kept HttpClient 4 runtime jars available for legacy plugin compatibility while keeping the built-in HTTP Request sampler on HttpClient 5.</li>
  <li>Added Brotli and Zstandard response decoding alongside gzip and deflate.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Controllers, Scheduling, and Flow Control</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added native Parallel Controller execution with bounded parallel sampler scheduling and HTTP state safeguards.</li>
  <li>Added Fork Controller for asynchronous child branches that share virtual-user context and complete before thread teardown.</li>
  <li>Added unified Thread Group scheduling controls with closed/open model selection.</li>
  <li>Added closed-model phases so a schedule can combine different ramp-up speeds, hold periods, and thread targets.</li>
  <li>Added open-model schedule helpers, even-arrival scheduling, max active thread limits, safe schedule parsing, and graph preview support.</li>
  <li>Added Thread Group pacing controls.</li>
  <li>Cleared runtime user variables on new iterations when same-user mode is disabled, while preserving initial variables.</li>
  <li>Added Pause and Resume in the GUI and on the UDP command port, with <code>bin/pause.*</code> and <code>bin/resume.*</code> wrappers.</li>
  <li>Improved shutdown so it no longer waits for timers to complete and only waits for in-flight server responses to finish cleanly.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>GUI and Test-Plan Editing</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Modernized the GUI with a cleaner light/dark look and more compact tree/editing layouts.</li>
  <li>Added undo and redo for semantic tree edits including add, delete, update, move, and search/replace operations.</li>
  <li>Added background JMX loading with a loading overlay.</li>
  <li>Added opt-in fast GUI loading through <code>jmeter.gui.load.fast=true</code>.</li>
  <li>JMX files with missing plugin elements now load with disabled placeholders instead of failing the whole file.</li>
  <li>Improved Search Tree flagging for pre-processors, post-processors, assertions, timers, and config elements.</li>
  <li>Added selective removal of matching search results with confirmation so bulk cleanup can avoid accidental parent-node deletion.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Scripting, Data, and Correlation</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Added structured If and While Controller condition rows with all/any matching, while preserving legacy condition expressions.</li>
  <li>Added loop/while index behavior options and exported index variable display.</li>
  <li>Added Transaction Controller measurement modes plus built-in delay and pacing controls.</li>
  <li>Added extractor fail-on-no-match options for Boundary, CSS/HTML, Regex, XPath, XPath2, JSONPath, and JMESPath extractors.</li>
  <li>Added random-order reading for CSV Data Set records.</li>
  <li>Added CSV preview of the first sample variable assignments.</li>
  <li>Focused scripting on JSR223/Groovy by removing legacy BeanShell, BSF/JEXL2, Rhino JavaScript, and LogKit paths.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Visual Debugging and HAR Migration</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>View Results Tree now shows richer request/response diagnostics, endpoint details, HTTP/TLS metadata, cookies, variables, binary/text detection, and jump-to-source.</li>
  <li>BreakTest JMX metadata preserves origin and source-path information for debugging tools.</li>
  <li>HAR-backed recorded request/response tabs appear in View Results Tree and HTTP sampler editors when matching BreakTest HAR metadata is available.</li>
  <li>Recorded-vs-replayed diffs make HAR migration and HTTP/2 replay debugging easier.</li>
  <li>Transaction child samples preserve source test-element paths so folded transaction results can still navigate to the correct source element.</li>
  <li>HTTP/2 replay removes unsupported hop-by-hop headers and normalizes request/status lines for cleaner diffs.</li>
  <li>Host-only cookie matching is stricter so cookies do not leak to unrelated hosts or subdomains.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility Notes</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Existing JMeter JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li>Many package names, property names, command internals, and Maven coordinates intentionally still use <code>jmeter</code> or <code>org.apache.jmeter</code> for compatibility.</li>
  <li>BreakTest-specific JMX metadata may not round-trip into older JMeter versions.</li>
  <li>Plugins that depend on removed internals may need migration.</li>
  <li>RMI Remote Server style distributed execution is removed. Use BreakTest Enterprise or another controlled orchestration layer for distributed tests.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Legal and Attribution</ch_section>
<p>
BreakTest is a derivative work of Apache JMeter. Apache JMeter copyright and
attribution notices are retained in the source tree and distribution notices.
BreakTest is independent from The Apache Software Foundation and is not
affiliated with, endorsed by, or sponsored by The Apache Software Foundation.
</p>

</section>
</body>
</document>
