<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>
<properties>
    <author email="info@breakingit.nl">BreakTest developers</author>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Release Notes">

<h1>BreakTest 2026.07.19 - HTTP/3 over QUIC Beta</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.19 introduces beta HTTP/3 sampling over QUIC on Java 26,
while retaining Java 21 compatibility for the rest of BreakTest. It also makes
non-GUI startup faster, keeps validation independent of workload scheduling,
and improves settings and modern-JDK compatibility.
</p>

<ch_section>HTTP/3 over QUIC Beta</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Adds HTTP/3 as an explicit HTTP Request protocol, powered by the Java 26 <code>java.net.http</code> QUIC implementation.</li>
  <li>Supports HTTP/3-only requests, direct HTTP/3 with TCP fallback, and optional browser-like Alt-Svc discovery for default-protocol samplers.</li>
  <li>Set <code>httpsampler.http3.prefer_for_default=true</code> to upgrade compatible default samplers after a server advertises Alt-Svc.</li>
  <li>Records the negotiated HTTP version, destination endpoint, and TLS version in sample results.</li>
  <li>Reuses clients per thread, supports interruption and lifecycle cleanup, and maps QUIC failures to concise network error codes.</li>
  <li>Identifies HTTP/3 over QUIC explicitly in timeout and other HTTP/3 error details.</li>
  <li>On Java 21-25, selecting HTTP/3 logs one warning and falls back to negotiated HTTP/2 or HTTP/1.1.</li>
</ul>
<p>
HTTP/3 support is beta. Explicit HTTP/3 samplers currently reject proxies and
multipart uploads. Default samplers using those features remain on HttpClient 5.
The JDK QUIC stack requires its built-in trust manager, so JMeter
client-certificate keystores and lenient certificate trust do not apply to
HTTP/3 requests.
</p>

<ch_section>HTTP Request Compatibility</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>HTTP/2 requests send the exact <code>content-length</code> whenever the request content length is known, including <code>content-length: 0</code> for an empty POST, as recommended by RFC 9110.</li>
  <li>HAR imports recognize unmarked Chromium memory-cache reuses and omit them from replay without letting their sparse contextual headers replace the original network request headers.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Faster Startup and Modern Java</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Caches classpath scan results and invalidates them when the runtime JAR set changes.</li>
  <li>Creates and reuses a per-Java-version AppCDS archive for non-GUI launches; set <code>BREAKTEST_CDS=off</code> to disable it.</li>
  <li>Avoids legacy XStream Unsafe and final-field mutation probes by using the pure-Java reflection provider.</li>
  <li>Enables native access for packaged launches to avoid FlatLaf warnings on recent JDKs.</li>
  <li>Keeps the Gradle daemon on Java 21 for reproducible builds while packaged BreakTest supports Java 21 and newer.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Validation, Archives, and Settings</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Runs validation as one closed-model thread and one iteration regardless of the source Thread Group model.</li>
  <li>Stops validation when that iteration completes instead of waiting for an open-model schedule.</li>
  <li>Identifies compressed JMX archives before normal-file load events, preventing plugin analysis from parsing ZIP data as XML.</li>
  <li>Uses compact Settings rows with visible defaults and adds an Overrides tab for user, system, and command-line values.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX plans continue to load and save normally.</li>
  <li>HTTP/3-specific JMX values can be opened on Java 21-25 and use the documented HTTP/2 or HTTP/1.1 fallback.</li>
  <li>Java 21 or later is required; Java 26 or later is required for HTTP/3 over QUIC.</li>
  <li>This release uses the direct Git tag <code>2026.07.19</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h1>BreakTest 2026.07.17 - HAR Import and HTTP Request Controls</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.17 streamlines transaction-aware HAR imports, clarifies
redirect handling, and keeps generated HTTP samplers compatible with native
JMeter JMX metadata.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Makes the HAR importer more compact and hides idle-based transaction splitting when a recording already contains explicit transactions.</li>
  <li>Shows estimated compressed storage sizes for each request and response retention choice.</li>
  <li>Removes redundant importer choices and increases the default randomized transaction delay range to 5-25 seconds.</li>
  <li>Moves request options and timeouts to the Advanced tab in a compact layout.</li>
  <li>Replaces two mutually exclusive redirect checkboxes with one selector for no redirects, retaining each redirect response, or retaining only the final response.</li>
  <li>Preserves native JMeter redirect properties when loading and saving JMX files.</li>
  <li>Writes native HTTP sampler <code>testclass</code> metadata during HAR conversion so compact JMX output retains sampler identity and transaction attribution.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>HAR Import Workflow</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Dedicated BreakTest HAR recordings with explicit transaction markers no longer show the inapplicable idle transaction threshold.</li>
  <li>Storage choices report their estimated compressed size using the current HAR data.</li>
  <li>The importer removes the continue-on-error control and the redundant all-except-static-resources retention mode.</li>
  <li>Request indexing, dynamic URL detection, transaction delay, and storage choices remain available in a smaller dialog.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>HTTP Request Controls</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Follow Redirects and Redirect Automatically are represented by one mutually exclusive selector in HTTP Request and recorder settings.</li>
  <li>Existing <code>HTTPSampler.follow_redirects</code> and <code>HTTPSampler.auto_redirects</code> values map to the new selector without changing native JMX compatibility.</li>
  <li>Retaining each response preserves intermediate redirect sub-results; final-response-only mode delegates redirect handling to the HTTP client.</li>
  <li>Advanced request options use a horizontal layout to reduce scrolling.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>HAR-generated HTTP samplers include both <code>guiclass</code> and <code>testclass</code> metadata, matching native JMeter elements and supporting downstream listener transaction matching.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files retain their redirect behavior when opened and saved.</li>
  <li>Java 21 or later is required.</li>
  <li>This release uses the direct Git tag <code>2026.07.17</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h1>BreakTest 2026.07.16 - Load Profiles and Network Diagnostics</h1>
<p>
BreakTest 2026.07.16 adds clearer closed-model load profiles, hardens parallel
controller restarts, and makes common HTTP network failures easier to identify
from results and reports. It also restores reliable installation and relaunch
for updates prepared from the GUI.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Adds a <b>Load Profile</b> selector that switches closed-model Thread Groups between familiar Standard settings and phase-based Custom scheduling.</li>
  <li>Interprets <code>threadsPhase(targetThreads, durationSeconds)</code> durations relative to the preceding phase.</li>
  <li>Keeps pacing, same-user behaviour, and delayed thread creation available for Custom profiles.</li>
  <li>Fixes stale marker handshakes in Parallel, Fork, and parallel ForEach controllers after loop restarts.</li>
  <li>Uses concise HTTP failure codes such as <code>Connect timeout</code>, <code>Response timeout</code>, and <code>Connection reset</code>.</li>
  <li>Adds duration and host/IP context to timeout and reset messages without synthetic unavailable-value placeholders.</li>
  <li>Continues to package the Chrome, Edge, and Firefox recorder from its pinned standalone repository checkout.</li>
  <li>Fixes the detached updater's standalone classpath so a prepared update installs after the GUI exits and then relaunches BreakTest.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Closed-Model Load Profiles</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Standard and Custom profiles show only the controls that apply to the selected mode, keeping the load graph close to active settings.</li>
  <li>Custom phases express ramp-up, steady load, ramp-down, and initial delay with a target thread count and duration for each successive phase.</li>
  <li>Phase graphs and runtime scheduling use the same cumulative timeline.</li>
  <li>Custom profiles retain pacing plus shared same-user and delayed-thread-creation options.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Controller Restart Reliability</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Parallel Controller clears in-flight marker handshakes when a thread loop restarts after an error or flow-control action.</li>
  <li>Fork Controller and parallel ForEach apply the same reset invariant so later iterations cannot consume stale marker state.</li>
  <li>Regression coverage exercises restart paths for all three controllers.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>HTTP Network Diagnostics</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Connect, response, reset, refused, unknown-host, and no-route failures use short response codes and readable messages instead of Java class names.</li>
  <li>Wrapped HttpClient 5 socket timeouts are classified from the configured connect and response timeout values, including TLS-handshake timeout shapes.</li>
  <li>Connection-reset messages include the hostname and resolved endpoint when available.</li>
  <li>Recognized network failures use compact result bodies without stack traces or synthetic unavailable-value placeholders.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Distribution and Compatibility</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Browser recorder sources are maintained in the standalone <code>breaktest-browser-extension</code> repository and remain included under <code>browser-extension/</code> in release archives.</li>
  <li>The updater installer is validated in a separate JVM using only its packaged runtime, including successful installation and relaunch coverage.</li>
  <li>Java 21 or later is required.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li>This release uses the direct Git tag <code>2026.07.16</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h1>BreakTest 2026.07.13 - Initial Community Release</h1>
<p>
BreakTest is a modern, JMeter-compatible performance testing tool for building,
debugging, validating, and running test plans against systems operated by your
own organization. This initial Community release combines a faster runtime,
modern protocols, advanced workload modelling, browser recording, portable
test evidence, richer diagnostics, and AI-assisted scripting.
</p>

<ch_section>Highlights</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>A redesigned desktop experience with modern themes, richer HTTP editing, searchable settings, enhanced results, and live performance reporting.</li>
  <li>A leaner runtime with lazy decompression, configurable response retention, lightweight cloning, lazy diagnostics, and fewer hot-path allocations. Measured scenarios show roughly 50–80% lower memory use and up to 50% lower CPU use, depending on the test plan and workload.</li>
  <li>First-class HTTP/2 support powered by Apache HttpClient 5.</li>
  <li>Parallel Controller and parallel ForEach model browser-style concurrency instead of processing every embedded request sequentially.</li>
  <li>Fork Controller supports asynchronous polling and background flows while the main virtual-user journey continues.</li>
  <li>Unified open and closed workload models provide realistic concurrency, flexible scheduling, traffic shaping, and thread-level pacing.</li>
  <li>Local Chrome, Edge, and Firefox browser recorders export transaction-aware HAR files for guided import into BreakTest.</li>
  <li>Recorded-versus-replayed request and response comparisons make scripting, debugging, and correlation faster.</li>
  <li>Improved tree flagging, search-and-replace, and semantic undo and redo make large test plans safer to edit.</li>
  <li>AI-assisted scripting and repair through Codex, Claude Code, and MCP-based workflows apply changes transactionally and provide recovery safeguards.</li>
  <li>Portable compressed <code>.jmx</code> plans can embed HAR or replay evidence, attachments, request bodies, response bodies, and checksums.</li>
  <li>Native UDP Request and UDP Receiver samplers provide configurable codecs, timeouts, local binding, and reusable per-user sockets.</li>
  <li>Running schedules can be paused and resumed, and Transaction Controllers support built-in think time and pacing.</li>
  <li>Extractors can fail a sampler when an expected correlation value is missing.</li>
  <li>Verified in-application updates support rollback and restart while preserving user configuration, plugins, and driver libraries.</li>
  <li>BreakTest-specific materials are released under the BreakTest Community Source License 1.0.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Browser Recording and HAR Import</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Browser recorder extensions for Chrome, Chromium-based Edge, and Firefox ship under <code>browser-extension/</code> in binary and source distributions.</li>
  <li>Recording can begin in a prepared blank tab or private context so the first navigation and dependent resources are captured.</li>
  <li>Transaction names assigned during recording become Transaction Controllers during import.</li>
  <li>Optional cache disabling supports cold-cache recordings, and unavailable browser response bodies are reported clearly.</li>
  <li>The guided <b>File &gt; Import HAR...</b> workflow supports hostname selection, request grouping, error handling, request indexes, dynamic URLs, headers, and configurable transaction delays.</li>
  <li>Generated plans can include Transaction Controllers, Parallel Controllers, HTTP Request Defaults, Cookie Managers, assertions, and preserved recording metadata.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Portable Test Plans and Recorded Evidence</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>New <code>.jmx</code> files use a compressed archive while retaining the familiar extension; legacy plain-XML JMX files continue to load.</li>
  <li>Plans can carry referenced attachments and filtered HAR or replay evidence without extracting content to the filesystem.</li>
  <li>Recording retention can keep all traffic, omit static bodies, omit static resources, or exclude recording evidence.</li>
  <li>Request and response bodies are deduplicated and linked through validated references and checksums.</li>
  <li><b>Store Replay</b> captures the latest replayed traffic as the plan's current evidence bundle.</li>
  <li>Recorded and replayed evidence remains available after reopening for sampler inspection, result analysis, and comparison.</li>
  <li>Archive paths, linked content, required dependencies, and checksums are validated before use.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Modern HTTP and Native UDP</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Apache HttpClient 5 powers the built-in HTTP/1.1 and asynchronous HTTP/2 sampler paths.</li>
  <li>HTTP/2 supports explicit and preferred selection, negotiated fallback, connect timing, upload lengths, safer replay, and conservative closed-session retry.</li>
  <li>HTTP clients and reactor threads are reused where safe to reduce connection churn and resource consumption.</li>
  <li>NTLM authentication resolves variables before asynchronous challenge callbacks.</li>
  <li>Responses support gzip, deflate, Brotli, and Zstandard, with lazy decompression when content is not inspected.</li>
  <li>HttpClient 4 libraries remain bundled for legacy plugin compatibility while built-in HTTP Requests use HttpClient 5.</li>
  <li>UDP Request supports request/response and fire-and-forget datagrams, timeouts, local binding, unreachable-destination handling, and named socket reuse.</li>
  <li>UDP Receiver consumes later datagrams from named sockets and supports successful or failing timeout behaviour.</li>
  <li>UDP payloads support UTF-8, hexadecimal, and single-byte text plus the native <code>UDPTrafficCodec</code> extension point.</li>
  <li>Datagram size, truncation, buffer reuse, and per-user socket isolation are handled across sequential, parallel, and forked execution.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Workload Modelling, Scheduling, and Concurrency</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Parallel Controller executes bounded concurrent branches with HTTP state safeguards.</li>
  <li>ForEach Controller supports configurable parallel execution and lazily creates branches for very large collections.</li>
  <li>Fork Controller starts asynchronous child flows that share virtual-user context and finish before thread teardown.</li>
  <li>Groovy and JSR223 scripts can call <code>stopForks()</code> or <code>stopForksNow()</code> without stopping the main virtual user.</li>
  <li>Parallel and fork workers isolate mutable sampler, loop, status, transaction, and compiler state while preserving intentional shared variables.</li>
  <li>Nested parallel sections and parent-mode transactions retain deterministic source mappings, status, and listener behaviour.</li>
  <li>The standard Thread Group supports closed and open models, phases, even arrivals, maximum active threads, graph previews, and safe schedule parsing.</li>
  <li>Pacing and transaction delay modes support fixed, random, Gaussian, recorded, or disabled delays.</li>
  <li>Pause and Resume work through the GUI and command port, and shutdown wakes timers while allowing in-flight responses to finish.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>AI-Assisted Scripting and Repair</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>BreakTest integrates with Codex, Claude Code, opencode, and MCP-compatible agents for guided plan inspection and repair.</li>
  <li>GUI-backed tools find, clone, move, edit, and safely delete live nodes while preserving complete subtrees.</li>
  <li>Repair planning detects conflicting dynamic values and proposes native Regex Extractors only when recording evidence supports a safe pattern.</li>
  <li>Quoted values, duplicate replacements, stale identifiers, and orphaned extractor scenarios are handled explicitly.</li>
  <li>Repair batches are transactional, with GUI undo and backup restoration when integrity cannot be preserved.</li>
  <li>Protected-container checks, exact match counts, stable path fallback, null-safe refresh, and full diagnostics reduce unsafe edits.</li>
  <li>Incomplete repair runs report a blocked status instead of appearing successful.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Desktop Authoring Experience</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>A refreshed FlatLaf interface provides consistent light and dark themes, updated icons, cleaner trees, and improved menus.</li>
  <li>The HTTP Request editor provides a compact URL bar and Params, Headers, Body, Files, and Advanced tabs with value counts.</li>
  <li>Sampler-specific HTTP headers live on the HTTP Request; legacy child Header Managers migrate automatically and scoped managers remain supported.</li>
  <li>Semantic undo and redo covers add, delete, update, move, and search and replace operations.</li>
  <li>Large plans load in the background, optional fast loading reduces normalisation cost, and missing plugins become disabled placeholders.</li>
  <li>Search Tree recognises processors, assertions, timers, and configuration elements, with safeguarded selective removal.</li>
  <li>Tree nodes show child counts, transactions show delay summaries, and request tabs expose hidden data counts.</li>
  <li>View Results can detach and dock, validation can target selected thread groups, and the log and AI panel is easier to resize.</li>
  <li>A searchable Settings screen provides typed editors, defaults, modified indicators, reset controls, and local override persistence.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Results, Diagnostics, and Performance Reporting</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>View Results provides Tree and Table layouts with timing, latency, connection, size, thread, label, URL, and status data.</li>
  <li>Selectable sortable columns, filters, tooltips, and stable live scrolling make large result sets easier to inspect.</li>
  <li>Diagnostics include endpoint, HTTP, TLS, cookie, variable, binary/text, and source-element information.</li>
  <li>HAR-backed tabs compare recorded and replayed traffic, normalize HTTP/2 differences, and retain navigation through folded transactions.</li>
  <li>The Performance Report listener provides throughput, bandwidth, error, connect-time, median, P75, P90, P95, and P99 metrics.</li>
  <li>Error response times can be excluded from timing calculations, with clear guidance about percentile retention cost.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Runtime Efficiency and Reliability</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Response retention can keep compressed bytes, discard successes, retain only failures, or store checksums instead of bodies.</li>
  <li>Lightweight cloning and shared safe property state reduce per-thread object churn.</li>
  <li>Rich sample metadata is listener-driven and allocated only when diagnostics require it.</li>
  <li>Header merging, temporary properties, response buffers, parent paths, and controller traversal are optimized for hot paths.</li>
  <li>Fork tasks, executors, timers, samplers, and controller mappings are cleaned up promptly and by identity.</li>
  <li>Parallel ForEach retains state proportional to active parallelism rather than total collection size.</li>
  <li>Archives, concurrency, updater rollback, HAR conversion, GUI lifecycle, and high-capacity controllers have regression and benchmark coverage.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Scripting, Data, and Correlation</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>If and While Controllers support structured all or any condition rows while retaining legacy expressions.</li>
  <li>Loop and While Controllers expose configurable index behaviour and exported index variables.</li>
  <li>Transaction Controllers provide measurement, delay, and pacing controls.</li>
  <li>Boundary, CSS/HTML, Regex, XPath, XPath2, JSONPath, and JMESPath extractors can fail samples when no match is found.</li>
  <li>CSV Data Set supports random record order and previews initial variable assignments.</li>
  <li>Scripting focuses on JSR223 and Groovy; legacy BeanShell, BSF/JEXL2, Rhino JavaScript, and LogKit paths are removed.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Distribution and Updates</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Distributions use a stable <code>breaktest/</code> directory and ship browser recorder extensions alongside the runtime.</li>
  <li><code>breaktest.jar</code>, <code>BREAKTEST_HOME</code>, <code>BREAKTEST_OPTS</code>, and <code>BREAKTEST_LANGUAGE</code> are the preferred runtime names.</li>
  <li>BreakTest-owned Maven artifacts use the <code>nl.breakingit.breaktest</code> group.</li>
  <li>GUI update checks run at startup and periodically and are also available through <b>Help &gt; Check for Updates</b>.</li>
  <li>Downloads require the expected binary ZIP, SHA-512 checksum, and matching GitHub SHA-256 digest.</li>
  <li>Installation runs after exit, rolls back failed replacement, restarts after success, and preserves properties, plugins, and driver libraries.</li>
  <li>Extraction and installation paths reject traversal and symlink escapes, and source checkouts are never modified.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Compatibility Notes</ch_section>
<ul>
  <li>Java 21 or later is required.</li>
  <li>Existing JMeter-compatible JMX files remain supported where practical.</li>
  <li>Compressed JMX archives require a compatible BreakTest version, and embedded recordings are a BreakTest extension.</li>
  <li>Many package names, properties, command internals, and compatibility coordinates retain <code>jmeter</code> or <code>org.apache.jmeter</code> names.</li>
  <li>Plugins that depend on removed internals may require migration.</li>
  <li>Parallel ForEach is opt-in; existing controllers remain sequential unless explicitly enabled.</li>
  <li>RMI Remote Server-style execution is not included. Use BreakTest Enterprise or another controlled orchestration layer for distributed tests.</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Security Model</ch_section>
<p>
BreakTest follows the trusted-test-plan model. Treat JMX files as executable
input: a test plan can run scripts, load classes, read files, make network
requests, and interact with systems reachable from the runner. Only open or
execute plans you trust, or isolate them first. See SECURITY.md and
THREAT_MODEL.md for details.
</p>

<ch_section>License and Attribution</ch_section>
<p>
BreakTest-specific materials are licensed under the BreakTest Community Source
License 1.0. Community use is limited to testing systems operated by your own
organization. Excluded commercial uses require prior written permission or a
commercial license from Breaking IT. Requests may be sent to
<code>info@breakingit.nl</code>.
</p>
<p>
BreakTest is a derivative work of Apache JMeter. Applicable copyright, license,
and attribution notices for Apache JMeter and other third-party materials are
retained in the source tree and distribution. BreakTest is independent from
The Apache Software Foundation and is not affiliated with, endorsed by, or
sponsored by The Apache Software Foundation.
</p>

</section>
</body>
</document>
