<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>
<properties>
    <title>Issues</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Issue tracker">
  <p>
    BreakTest uses GitHub Issues for BreakTest-specific bugs, regressions,
    feature requests, and documentation feedback.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://github.com/Breaking-IT/breaktest/issues">Open BreakTest issues</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://github.com/Breaking-IT/breaktest/issues/new/choose">Create a new BreakTest issue</a></li>
    <li><a href="security.html">Report a security issue privately</a></li>
  </ul>
  <note>
    BreakTest is independent from The Apache Software Foundation. If you are
    reporting a behavior difference from Apache JMeter, please include the
    Apache JMeter version you compared against.
  </note>
</section>

<section name="Support questions">
  <p>
    GitHub Issues are best for actionable BreakTest bugs and feature requests.
    For usage questions, include a minimal JMX file, the exact BreakTest version,
    Java version, operating system, and what you already tried. If your question
    is about generic JMeter-compatible test-plan modeling, upstream Apache JMeter
    community resources may still be useful background, but BreakTest issues
    should stay focused on BreakTest behavior.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Requesting an enhancement">
  <p>
    Please check whether the same enhancement has already been requested. If a
    similar issue exists, add detail to the existing discussion instead of
    opening a duplicate.
  </p>
  <p>
    Good feature requests describe the use case first. For BreakTest, it is
    especially helpful to say whether the request affects compatibility with
    existing JMX files, resource usage, HTTP/2 behavior, controller semantics,
    GUI editing, AI-assisted scripting, or BreakTest Enterprise handoff.
  </p>
  <p>
    If you already have a concrete implementation, open a pull request from a
    fork. Small documentation fixes do not need a separate issue.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Raising an issue">
  <p>
    First check the <a href="https://github.com/Breaking-IT/breaktest/issues">BreakTest issue tracker</a>.
    If the issue appears to be inherited from Apache JMeter, please say so and
    include the upstream version you tested. If the behavior is specific to a
    BreakTest feature, include enough detail for maintainers to reproduce it.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Required information for bug reporting">
<p>
Please provide enough information for others to reproduce the report:
</p>
<ul>
<li>BreakTest version, for example <code>2026.07.11</code></li>
<li>Java version, from <code>java -version</code>; BreakTest requires Java 21 or later</li>
<li>Operating system and architecture</li>
<li><code>jmeter.log</code> or other relevant log files, after checking for secrets</li>
<li>Minimal JMX file if relevant, with secrets and private endpoints redacted</li>
<li>JTL/result files if relevant, with sensitive information redacted</li>
<li>Whether third-party plugins are required to reproduce the behavior</li>
<li>Whether the same plan behaves differently in Apache JMeter 5.6.3</li>
<li>Steps to reproduce, expected behavior, and actual behavior</li>
<li>Screenshots or screen recordings for GUI issues</li>
</ul>
<p>
New source files should use the existing Apache License header style used in
this repository. Do not add <code>@author</code> tags; credit is handled through
Git history and release notes.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
