<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  ~ contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  ~ this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  ~ (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  ~ the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="info@breakingit.nl">BreakTest Project</author>
    <title>Community Guidelines</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Community guidelines">

<p>
BreakTest coordinates public development through GitHub issues and pull
requests. Please keep discussions focused, respectful, and reproducible.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
      Respect the discussion type
</strong><br/>
There are generally two types of public project discussions.
</p>

<p>
<ul>
    <li>
    Issues for bugs, regressions, feature requests, and documentation feedback.
    </li>
    <li>
    Pull requests for concrete changes that are ready for review.
    </li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
<strong>
      Use the right project.
</strong><br/>
BreakTest is independent from Apache JMeter. Use BreakTest issues for
BreakTest bugs and features. If you are discussing upstream Apache JMeter
itself, use the upstream Apache JMeter project channels.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Ask actionable questions.  </strong><br/>
Include the BreakTest version, Java version, operating system, a minimal JMX
file when possible, and a clear description of expected and actual behavior.
For compatibility issues, include the Apache JMeter version you compared
against.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Give feedback when you get a good answer.  </strong><br/>

If a response helped you solve a problem, add the resolution to the issue or
pull request. Future users will find that context.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Keep your email short and to the point; use a suitable subject line.
</strong><br/>
Long reports are fine when the detail is useful, but lead with the problem,
the expected behavior, and a minimal reproduction. Keep unrelated questions in
separate issues.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Start a new issue for a new topic
</strong><br/>
Do not append unrelated questions to an existing issue. New topics are easier
to triage, search, and close correctly.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
Please don't send attachments or include large chunks of code</strong><br/>
Before attaching JMX, JTL, screenshots, logs, or HAR files, remove secrets,
tokens, customer data, and private endpoints. If a file is too large, create a
small reproduction instead.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Report security issues privately.
</strong><br/>
Do not open public issues or pull requests for undisclosed vulnerabilities.
Use the <a href="security.html">security policy</a>.
</p>

<p>
<strong>
    Do not duplicate reports.
</strong><br/>
If you have more information for an existing issue, add it there instead of
creating a second copy.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Conclusion">
<p>
<strong>Now that you have read the guidelines above</strong>, see
<a href="./mail2.html">the community page</a> for the current BreakTest
discussion channels.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
